National Plastics Center & Museum Records
National Plastics Center & Museum Records
1925-2008
National Plastics Center & Museum
4 linear ft.
Collection consists of administrative records, financial records, and publicity materials from the Museum in Leominster, Massachusetts.
4150871
Biographical History
The National Plastics Center & Museum was located in Leominster, Mass. in the former Lancaster Street School building. It was incorporated as a non-profit in 1982, long after plastics had become integral to everyday life, but during a time when the effects of plastics production and consumption were being widely debated. The National Plastics Center & Museum was thus founded not only to preserve the foundations and past of the plastics industry, but also to help educate the public about plastics and intervene in public discourse, highlighting the contributions of plastic to the overall quality of modern life, and how the plastics industry was contributing toward environmental sustainability.
In addition to maintaining permanent and rotating collections and accumulating artifacts, the National Plastics Center & Museum conducted public outreach, like their PlastiVan program, which travelled throughout the U.S. educating students and teachers about the chemistry, history, processing, and environmental issues around plastics. Starting in 2006, the Society of Plastics Industry provided professional management services to the institution. The National Plastics Center & Museum was closed in 2008, after struggling for several years to attain substantial attendance numbers.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The National Plastics Center & Museum Records contains records relating to the organization's inventories and artifacts, communications, budgets and financial statements, publicity materials, and press coverage.
Administrative records contains finding aids and inventories, trustee newsletters, administrative communications, conference materials, meeting minutes and agendas, town records, and documents about the museum's construction.
Financial records contains the organization's bank and financial statements, pledge records and payments, expense reports, budgets, and contractor invoices and estimates.
Publicity contains newsletters, membership packets, and brochures from the National Plastics Center & Museum, related newspaper, magazine, and journal clippings, and a promotional video.
Arrangement of the Collection
Arranged into series by topic.
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
Issues of Pioneer Valley News have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Industrial Design; Plastics; Robinson Plastics Corporation.; National Plastics Center & Museum.; Irvin I. Rubin Plastics Corporation.; Society of the Plastics Industry.; Society of Plastics Engineers.; State University of New York at Stony Brook. Waste Management Institute.; Plastics & molded products.; Plastics -- History.; Plastics -- Museums.; Plastics industry and trade.; Plastics industry and trade -- Congresses and conventions.; Leominster (Mass.) -- History.; Leominster (Mass.) -- Intellectual life.; Brochures.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; CD-ROMs.; Expense reports.; Financial statements.; Newsletters.; Photographs.; Video recordings.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from National Plastics Center & Museum, 11/06/2008.
Inventory
- Administrative records
  - Book inventory, 2005; inventory arranged by book numbers, titles, authors, and reference numbers (Oversize 1)
  - Communications
    - Flannagan, Richard, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Galvin, Jack, 1934; 1984-1985; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Keville, John, 1984-1986; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Kilcoyne, Mary, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Trustees, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1971; 1981-1994 (Box 1)
  - Conferences, 1987; 1989-1991; programs, letters, photographs, and preparatory materials (Box 1)
  - Conferences, 1973-1977; a binder of planning materials for RETEC conferences (Oversize 1)
  - Construction, 1931; 1975,; 1982-1985; communications with contractors and Leominster officials about the construction of the museum; also includes information about Lancaster Street School, which the museum took over (Box 2)
  - Doyle library and archives finding aids, 2007-2008; binder of finding aids for Museum collections (Oversize 1)
  - Grant proposal, 1998; proposal for Informal Science Education grant from the National Science Foundation (Box 2)
  - Information and material requests, 1993-1995; mostly requests for "Passing through" educational video and accompanying teacher's guide; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Meeting minutes and materials, 1970-1975; 1983-1985,; 1993-1994,; 1996,; 2000; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Pioneer Valley SPE secretary reports, 1982-1983 (Oversize 1)
  - Plastics & Molded Products, indexes and contents, vols. 1-11, 1925-1934; 1998; a binder containing photocopies of indexes and tables of contents of Plastics and molded products (Oversize 1)
  - Program evaluations, circa 1993-1995; teacher evaluations about "Passing through" educational film and accompanying teacher's guide (Box 3)
  - Town and school records, 1928; 1932-1936,; 1944-1948,; 1954-1957,; 1983; city council agendas and notes, Leominster street list, property assessments, assorted letters (Box 3)
  - Trustee newsletters, 1984-1986 (Box 3)
  - Waste Management Institute, 1989; communications and notes regarding the Waste Management Institute at SUNY Stony Brook (Box 3)
  - Memorabilia, 1997; undated; 2 ribbons and 1 Gala pin (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939; 1955,; 1984-1988,; 1991,; 1993,; 2002-2008,; undated; photographs, "The future is in your hands" training manual, contact lists, notes, and letters; 3 folders (Box 3)
- Financial records
  - Bank statements, Guaranty Bank & Trust Co., 1972-1975; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Bank statements, Shawmut Worcester County Bank, 1981-1983 (Box 4)
  - Checks, 1972-1977; also includes handwritten notes (Box 4)
  - Contributions and pledges, 1982-1985; 1993-1994; checks, annual pledge reports, communications, and pledge postcards (Box 4)
  - Construction and design, 1984-1985; communications with contractors and invoices (Box 4)
  - Expense reports, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Expense reports, John Keville, 1988 (Box 4)
  - Financial statements, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Ledgers and notes, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
  - Paid invoices, 1982-1983; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Raffle records, 1983 (Box 5)
  - SPE budgets, 1975-1978 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1939; 1982-1985; insurance contract, invoices, land appraisal, and various notes (Box 5)
- Publicity
  - Brochures, undated; includes brochures from Plastics Institute of America, Somoltec, and the National Plastics Center & Museum (Box 5)
  - Invitations, 1969; 1984,; 2001-2002; invitations to events hosted by the National Plastics Center & Museum and the Solar Chemical Corporation (Box 5)
  - Newsletters, 1979-1980; 1995-2000,; 2003-2008 (Box 5)
  - Newspapers and magazines, 1929; 1942,; 1956,; 1966,; 1976-1977,; 1979,; undated (Box 5)
  - Newspapers and magazines, 1982-1989; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Newspapers and magazines, 1991-2005; undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Promotional video, "Wow them now!", 2003; npc_001; includes letter to board members announcing the new video; printed on the CD is a color photo of the National Plastics Center and Museum building in Leominster; 1 CD-ROM (Box 6)
  - Publicity and membership packets, undated (Box 6)